Guide to the John Jay Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
John Jay Papers,
1668-[ca. 1862]
Jay, John, 1745-1829.
ca. 10,500 items (69 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078947
Biographical Note
American Chief Justice, diplomat.
Scope and Content
Letters, manuscripts, documents, and letterbooks of Jay and of many members of his family. The letters touch on every aspect of American life and government of the period, and contain correspondence from such prominent individuals as John Adams, George Clinton, James Duane, Benjamin Franklin, Alexander Hamilton, Thomas Jefferson, Rufus King, John Paul Jones, Marquis de Lafayette, Robert B. Livingston, William Livingston, Gouverneur Morris, Robert Morris, Edmund Randolph, Philip Schuyler, and George Washington. There are approximately 500 letters from Jay, primarily drafts of correspondence to the persons listed above, as well as his correspondence as Secretary of Foreign Affairs, 1784-1789. The manuscripts and documents include many reports, commissions, and diplomas, as well as a draft copy of The Federalist Number 5 and Jay's oath of office as Chief Justice of the United States Supreme Court; also included are manumission documents, and a group of documents from Trinity Church, where his father was a vestryman from 1715 to 1785. The collection includes copies of Jay's letter book as Secretary of State, 10 Oct. 1788-25 Dec. 1792, and of four letters from John Armstrong, 19 June-27 Dec. 1810; and a copy of the pair of silverplated candlesticks from the Treaty of Paris, 3 Sept. 1783, reproduced by the Smithsonian Institution.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts and Documents
Series III: Miscellaneous Materials
Series IV: Oversized, Encased and Bound Materials
Subjects
United States.--Supreme Court.; United States.--Dept. of Foreign Affairs.--Office of the Secretary.; United States.--Dept. of State.; Trinity Church.; Adams, John, 1735-1826.; Clinton, George, 1739-1812.; Duane, James, 1733-1797.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; King, Rufus, 1755-1827.; Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834.; Livingston, Robert Burr, 1918-; Livingston, William, 1723-1790.; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816.; Morris, Robert, ca. 1745-1815.; Randolph, Edmund, 1753-1813.; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; United States--Social life and customs.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1783-1789.; African Americans--History.; Families--New York (State); Slaves--Emancipation.; Judges.; Statesmen.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1948 M-48 Gifts, purchases
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - A (Box 1)
  - Ba - Banyer, M., 1792 - 1815] (Box 2)
  - Banyer, M. [1816 - 1851 & n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Bar - Bl (Box 4)
  - Bo - Ca (Box 5)
  - Ce - Cla (Box 6)
  - Cli - Cu (Box 7)
  - D (Box 8)
  - E - F (Box 9)
  - G - Ham (Box 10)
  - Han - Jar (Box 11)
  - Jay, A. (Box 12)
  - Jay, E. - Jay, John, [n.d. & 1765 - 1777] (Box 13)
  - Jay, John, [1778 - July 1780] (Box 14)
  - Jay, John, [Aug. 1780 - Aug. 1781] (Box 15)
  - Jay, John, [Sept. 1781 - 1782] (Box 16)
  - Jay, John, [1783 - April 1784] (Box 17)
  - Jay, John, [May 1784 - Sept. 1785] (Box 18)
  - Jay, John, [Oct. 1785 - 1786] (Box 19)
  - Jay, John, [1787 - 1788] (Box 20)
  - Jay, John, [1789 - July 1794] (Box 21)
  - Jay, John, [Aug. 1794 - March 1795] (Box 22)
  - Jay, John, [April 1795 - 1798] (Box 23)
  - Jay, John, [1799 - 1804] (Box 24)
  - Jay, John, [1805 - 1809] (Box 25)
  - Jay, John, [1810 - 1812] (Box 26)
  - Jay, John, [1813 - 1817] (Box 27)
  - Jay, John, [1818 - 1821] (Box 28)
  - Jay, John, [1822 - 1828] (Box 29)
  - Jay, John Jr. - Jay, Peter (Box 30)
  - Jay, Peter Augustus, [1781 - 1804] (Box 31)
  - Jay, Peter Augustus, [1805 - 1813] (Box 32)
  - Jay, Peter Augustus, [1814 - 1823] (Box 33)
  - Jay, Peter Augustus, [1824 - 1839] (Box 34)
  - Jay, Peter Augustus, [1840 - 1843] (Box 35)
  - Jay, Sarah Livingston (Mrs. John), [1774 - 1776] (Box 35)
  - Jay, Sarah Livingston (Mrs. John), [1787 - 1802] (Box 36)
  - Jay, Sarah Louise & Jay, William, [1808 - 1832] (Box 37)
  - Jay, William, [1833 - 1840] (Box 38)
  - Jay, William, [1841 - 1855] (Box 39)
  - Jay, William [1856 - 1858] - Kent (Box 40)
  - Ki - Le (Box 41)
  - Li - Livingston, P.V.B. (Box 42)
  - Livingston, R.R. - Livingston, W. (Box 43)
  - Lo - Mad (Box 44)
  - Man - Morris, G. (Box 45)
  - Morris, J. - Mu (Box 46)
  - N - Pic (Box 47)
  - Pie - Rom (Box 48)
  - Roo - Sc (Box 49)
  - Se - St (Box 50)
  - Su - Tro (Box 51)
  - Tru - Va (Box 52)
  - Ve - end (Box 53)
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts and Documents
  - A - Cl (Box 54)
  - Co - Jay, James (Box 55)
  - Jay, John (1745 - 1829), [n.d. - 1789] (Box 56)
  - Jay, John (1745 - 1829), [1790 - 1800] (Box 57)
  - Jay, John (1745 - 1829), [1801 - end] (Box 58)
  - Jay, John (1817 - 1894) - Jay, William [ - 1883] (Box 59)
  - Jay, William [1884 - end] - P (Box 60)
  - R - end (Box 61)
  - Documents in the Case Hunt v. Underhill (Box 62)
- Series III: Miscellaneous Materials
  - Uncataloged Manuscripts and Documents -- Printed Material -- Portraits (Box 63)
  - Monaghan Purchase Inventory (Box 64)
  - Treaty of Paris Candlesticks (Box 65)
  - Genealogical file, A-O (Box 66)
  - Genealogical file, P-Z & Miscellaneous (Box 67)
- Series IV: Oversized, Encased and Bound Materials
  - Mayor's Court Ledger, 1758-1776
  - John Jay Letterbook, 24 Dec. 1779 - 19 Nov. 1782 (Box 1)
  - John Jay Letterbook, 10 Sept. 1782 - 25 July 1784 (and Appendix 20 - 27 Dec. 1779) (Box 2)
  - John Jay Letterbook, 5 Feb. 1785 - 16 Sept. 1788 (Box 3)
  - John Jay Letterbook, 29 Sept. 1779 - 12 July 1780 (Box 4)
    [Copies of letters by others]
  - John Jay Letterbook, 19 Oct. 1779 - 11 June 1780 (Box 5)
  - John Jay Letterbook, 2 July 1781 - 16 March 1782 (Box 6)
  - John Jay Letterbook, 21 May 1785 - 4 Oct. 1789 (Box 7)
    [Copies of correspondence regarding negotiations of Treaty with Spain]
  - John Jay Letterbook, 9 April 1794 - 5 March 1795 (Box 8)
  - John Jay Letterbook, 29 May 1787 - 8 July 1830 (Box 9)
  - John Jay Letterbook, 11 July 1795 - 29 Feb. 1896 (Box 10)
  - John Jay Circuit Court Diary, 16 April 1790 - 4 Aug. 1792 (Box 11)
  - John Jay Manuscripts Pertaining to Peace with Britain (Box 12)
  - John Jay Account Book of Letters Received, 15 Nov. 1781 - 1 Oct. 1782 (Box 13)
  - John Jay Receipt Book, 1789 - 1802 (Box 14)
  - John Jay Account Book of Jay's Mission to London, 1794 (Box 15)
  - Peter Jay Letterbook, 30 Dec. 1724 - 10 July 1735 (Box 16)
  - Peter Jay Letterbook, 9 Nov. 1745 - 16 Jan. 1748/9 (Box 17)
  - Peter Jay Letterbook, 17 Dec. 1748 - 20 Dec. 1772 (Box 18)
  - Sarah Livingston Jay (Mrs. John) Letterbook, [30 Dec. 1779] - 14 March 1783 (Box 19)
  - Sarah Livingston Jay (Mrs. John) Letterbook, 1779 - 1781 (Box 20)
  - Peter Jay Receipt Book, 1766 - 1782 (Box 21)
  - New York City Mayor's Court Ledger of Court Fees and Cases, 1758 -1776 (Box 22)